Sebastian Bernasek

Data Scientist | Chemical Engineer

San Francisco Bay Area

🛮 630-624-9699 | 🔀 sbernasek@gmail.com | 🏕 sbernasek.com | 🖸 sebastianbernasek | 🛅 sbernasek

Summary_

Chemical engineer turned data scientist with 5 years computational biology research and 3 years work experience as a process design engineer.

Skills

Data Engineering Analysis Computer Vision Modeling Coding Relational databases Hypothesis testing Feature extraction Stochastic processes Python & Cython Web scraping Bayesian inference Image segmentation Dynamical systems Package development Structured text & NLP Unsupervised learning Feature classification Nonlinear regression **REST APIs** Feature selection Networks & Time series Spatial analysis Classification Git, LaTeX, HTML/CSS Dimensionality reduction Visualization Quantitative microscopy Agent-based models Unix shell, OSX/Ubuntu

Education

Ph.D. in Chemical and Biological Engineering • 4.0 Northwestern University

2014 - 2019

- Center Scholar, NSF-Simons Center for Quantitative Biology
- Dissertation combines data science and chemical engineering to explore how cells make reliable decisions.

B.S. in Chemical Engineering • 3.8 • High Honors University of California, Santa Barbara

2008 - 2012

• Exchange student at Imperial College London throughout 2010/2011.

Experience

Personal Development & Consulting

Present

Took a year off to explore the world, helping out some friends along the way:

- Built a database of 5k+ targeted B2B sales leads using a combination of web-scraping, commercial APIs, and machine learning.
- Demystified a sales pipeline by using unstructured text profiles to predict client outcomes.
- · Automated PDF content extraction and parsing routines that will annually save hundreds of hours of tedious labor.

Researcher at Northwestern University Evanston, IL

2014 - 2019

- Published in high profile journals including Cell and PLOS Computational Biology.
- · Developed and deployed several simulation and analysis frameworks for the broader research community.

Day to day life entailed:

- Exploratory analysis of image and time series data.
- Developing creative strategies to derive insight from noisy experiments.
- Frequent collaboration with wet labs to design more valuable experiments.
- Brainstorming & hackathons for data-driven projects of all flavors.
- · Communicating complex ideas to diverse audiences.
- Lots of academic reading, writing, grant writing, and peer review.
- · Co-teaching undergraduate chemical engineering courses and data science bootcamps.
- Mentoring graduate, undergraduate, and high school students in formulating their own research.

Process Engineer at LanzaTech Chicago, IL

2012 - 2014

- Invented three processes for converting waste gases to lipid products. One patent granted, two more applications pending.
- Designed and built the company's core process modeling framework.
- Identified promising technology partners, ultimately leading to major investments.
- Modeled refinery-scale processes to predict and optimize economic and life-cycle performance.
- Advised executives and investors with technical analysis.

Research Assistant at UC Santa Barbara Santa Barbara, CA

2011 - 2012

· Conducted first ever dynamic measurement of interaction forces between vesicles. Published in Soft Matter

Summer Intern at UL Air Quality Sciences Atlanta, GA

Summer 2011

Publications

Ratio-based sensing of two transcription factors regulates the transit to differentiation.

Under Revision

Sebastian Bernasek*, J.F. Lachance*, N. Peláez*, R. Bakker, H. Navarro, L. Amaral, N. Bagheri, I. Rebay, R. Carthew

Expected 2020

Fly-QMA: Automated analysis of mosaic imaginal discs in Drosophila.

Published in PLOS Comp. Biology

Sebastian Bernasek, N. Peláez, R. Carthew, N. Bagheri, L. Amaral

2020

2019

Repressive gene regulation synchronizes neural development with cellular metabolism.

J. Cassidy*, Sebastian Bernasek*, R. Bakker, R. Giri, N. Peláez, B. Eder, A. Bobrowska, N. Bagheri, L. Amaral, R. Carthew

Published in Cell

Quantitative analysis of cell fate decisions.

Doctoral Dissertation

Sebastian Bernasek

500001015100010011

Direct measurement of interaction forces between charged multilamellar vesicles.

Published in Soft Matter

J. Frostad, M. Seth, Sebastian Bernasek, L.G. Leal

Patents_____

US Patent App. 62/872,869, Methods for Optimizing Gas Utilization.

LanzaTech

Sebastian Bernasek & Co-inventors

Filed 2019

US Patent App. 14/927,950, Fermentation process for the production of lipids.

LanzaTech

Sean Simpson and Sebastian Bernasek

Filed 2014

US Patent 9,783,835, Method for producing a lipid in a fermentation process.

LanzaTech

Sean Simpson and Sebastian Bernasek

Granted 2017

Software

FlyQMA

On PyPI

Python package for automated mosaic analysis of *Drosophila* imaginal discs. Facilitates high-throughput segmentation, bleedthrough correction, and annotation of raw microscope images in order to accelerate experimental pipelines while improving reproducibility.

FlyEye Analysis On PyPI

Python platform for analyzing gene expression dynamics in the developing fly eye. Ascribes quantitative rigor to a popular experimental technique by supporting dynamic analysis, spatial analysis, model fitting, and visualization of the resultant trends.

TFBinding On GitHub

Python package for simulating the statistical mechanics of cooperative binding events between transcription factors and their target promoters. Leverages a novel and highly-parallelizable microstate enumeration algorithm to dramatically outperform the existing state of the art in terms of both memory footprint and simulation scale.

GeneSSA On GitHub

A python framework for exact stochastic simulation of Markov processes, with a particular emphasis on gene regulatory networks. Simulates many classes of large networks faster and more efficiently than all other available software.

Mentorship _____

Simran Khunger High school student

Summer 2017

 $Project: \ Designing \ synthetic \ benchmarks \ for \ 3D \ segmentation \ of \ cell \ membranes \ in \ the \ larval \ \textit{Drosophila} \ eye.$

Darshan Patel Chemical engineering undergraduate

Summer 2016

Project: Probing tradeoffs between efficiency and robustness via in silico evolution of GRN topologies.

Teaching

Chemical Engineering Methods and Analysis

Spring 2018

Reaction Engineering and Kinetics	Spring 2017
Process Engineering and Design	Spring 2016
Data Science Bootcamp	Summer 2015
Reaction Engineering and Kinetics	Spring 2015